<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata version="1.0">
  <uniqueid id="org.sil.fonts.AwamiNastaliq.3.201" />
  <vendor name="SIL International" url="https://software.sil.org/wstech/" />
  <credits>
    <credit
      name="Sharon Correll"
      url="https://software.sil.org/wstech/"
      role="Script engineering, font design, and build support"
    />
    <credit
      name="Peter Martin"
      url="https://software.sil.org/wstech/"
      role="Lead designer"
    />
  </credits>
  <description>
    <text lang="en">
      Awami Nastaliq is a Nastaliq-style Arabic script font supporting a wide variety of
      languages of Southwest Asia, including but not limited to Urdu. This font is aimed
      at minority language support. This makes it unique among Nastaliq fonts.
      
      Awami means "of the people", "of the common population" or "public".
      
      The Awami Nastaliq font does not provide complete coverage of all the characters
      defined in Unicode for Arabic script. Because the font style is specifically
      intended for languages using the Nastaliq style of southwest Asia, the character
      set for this font is aimed at those languages.
      
      This font makes use of state-of-the-art font technologies to support complex
      typographic issues. Font smarts have been implemented using Graphite only. We have
      no current plans to support OpenType.
      
      Five fonts from this typeface family are included in this release:
      
      * Awami Nastaliq Regular
      * Awami Nastaliq Medium
      * Awami Nastaliq SemiBold
      * Awami Nastaliq Bold
      * Awami Nastaliq ExtraBold
      
      For detailed documentation see the contents of the 'documentation' folder.
      
      Awami Nastaliq is a trademark of SIL International.
      
      ## ChangeLog
      ---------
      (This should list both major and minor changes, most recent first.)
      
      ### 202x-Oct-xx (SIL WSTech team) Awami Nastaliq Version 3.300
      
      #### Improved
      -
      
      #### New
      - Added xxx characters:
      - U+
      
      ### 2023-Oct-23 (SIL WSTech team) Awami Nastaliq Version 3.200
      
      #### Improved
      - Fixed bug in dot removal for YEH followed by COMBINING Hamza (U+064A U+0654)
      - Fixed some minor kerning/collision/spacing bugs
      - Changed shape of mark on 06C7 (Arabic U) to look like a comma instead of a pesh
      - Created bold forms of the honorifics
      - Changed PUA codepoint U+E003 to U+FD47 ARABIC LIGATURE ALAYHI AS-SALAAM
      - Corrected weight class of Medium, SemiBold, and ExtraBold fonts
      
      #### New
      - Added six characters:
      - U+06A0 ARABIC LETTER AIN WITH THREE DOTS ABOVE
      - U+06AD ARABIC LETTER NG
      - U+06BD ARABIC LETTER NOON WITH THREE DOTS ABOVE
      - U+0762 ARABIC LETTER KEHEH WITH DOT ABOVE
      - U+FDCF ARABIC LIGATURE SALAAMUHU ALAYNAA
      - U+10ED0 ARABIC BIBLICAL END OF VERSE (this character is not officially in Unicode, it is in the pipeline for a future version of the Unicode Standard)
      
      ### 2023-Jan-30 (SIL WSTech team) Awami Nastaliq Version 3.100
      
      #### Improved
      - Fixed a bug that manifested as disappearing glyphs
      - Fixed some minor kerning/collision/spacing bugs
      
      ### 2022-Sep-20 (SIL WSTech team) Awami Nastaliq Version 3.000
      
      #### New
      
      - Added 4 weights -- Medium, SemiBold, Bold, and ExtraBold
      - Added three characters:
      - U+08C8 ARABIC LETTER GRAF
      - U+069B ARABIC LETTER SEEN WITH THREE DOTS BELOW
      - U+069C ARABIC LETTER SEEN WITH THREE DOTS BELOW AND THREE DOTS ABOVE
      
      #### Improved
      - Modified rules for forming the Allah ligature
      - Fixed a bug affecting the right margin
      - Fixed a problem with the behavior of the yeh with hamza
      - Added a short version of the final sad
      - Various improvements to beh forms
      - Collision fixes
      - Changed the default value of the short forms feature to use all short forms
      - Added a special form of khah+zabar+meem+jeem+heh-doachashmee to avoid excessive height
      - Flattened a couple of special ligatures
      - Changed dopesh to use 69 form consistently
      
      #### Removed
      - Removed "Small nuqtas" feature
      
      ### 2021-Apr-29 (SIL WSTech team) Awami Nastaliq Version 2.200
      - Improved spacing and kerning involving punctuation
      - Corrected nuqtas in dul character
      - Fixed collision bug that manifested itself in Paratext
      - Fixed other obscure bugs
      
      ### 2021-Jan-18 (SIL WSTech team) Awami Nastaliq Version 2.100
      - Added four honorific ligatures
      - U+FDFA ARABIC LIGATURE SALLALLAHOU ALAYHEWASALLAM
      - U+FDFB ARABIC LIGATURE JALLAJALALOUHOU
      - U+FDFD ARABIC LIGATURE BISMILLAH AR-RAHMAN AR-RAHEEM
      - U+E003 ALAYHI AS-SALAAM
      - Added U+075A DAL WITH INVERTED SMALL V BELOW
      - Adjusted shapes of lam + alef combination, certain reh forms, medial heh goal + reh
      - Adjusted position of honorific diacritics
      - Adjusted position of superscript-alef on lam
      - Added special ligature forms for three words
      - Added short forms of jeem+bariyeh, beh+qaf/waw, final jeem, final ain
      - Added wider form of jeem+kaf combination where needed
      - Improved alignment of kafs, alef, and bariyeh with the right margin
      - Increased spacing when sequences overlap
      - Improved kerning of punctuation
      - Improved kerning for rehs and other final forms
      - Improved connections with medial/final fehs
      
      ### 2019-Jun-19 (SIL WSTech team) Awami Nastaliq Version 2.000
      - Ten new characters - U+06C8, U+06CA, U+06CB, U+06CF, U+077E, U+077F, U+0695, U+06A4, U+08C7, U+221A
      - Adjust behavior of nuqtas over sequences of beh/teh/theh/peh/etc.
      - Changed shape of beh+seen and beh+sad before sad, tah, ain, feh, qaf, and final noon.
      - Improved glyph-shape approximations for automatic collision fixing
      - Adjusted diagonal cluster fitting involving short sequences
      - Adjusted shape of meem heads
      - Adjusted behavior of final-reh + zer
      - Added and tweaked anchors
      - Added smaller flat nukta for certain cases
      - Adjusted shape of pre-jeem medial lam, keheh and gaf
      - Adjusted position of salaam ulena ligature
      - Adjusted position of Arabic zero characters
      - Reduced size of U+060E
      - Fixed bugs in bariyeh attachments
      - Removed "Show invisible characters" feature
      - Fixed bug in "Hamza" feature (Arabic style setting)
      - Adjusted design of U+06BA (noon ghunna) to match Unicode recommendations
      - Tweaked glyph shapes and sizes
      
      ### 2018-Apr-24 (SIL NRSI team) Awami Nastaliq Version 1.101
      - Fixed bug in positioning of final reh
      
      ### 2018-Apr-03 (SIL NRSI team) Awami Nastaliq Version 1.100
      - Added characters: U+0604, U+0609, U+060A, U+060B, U+061C, U+0649, U+0659,
      U+066E, U+066F, U+0671, U+068E, U+069E, U+06A1, U+06B7, U+06C9, U+06E0,
      U+06E1, U+06EA, U+06ED, U+0763, U+0772, U+0773, U+0774, U+0775, U+0776,
      U+0777, U+0778, U+0779,	U+077A, U+077B, U+077C, U+077D, U+FDFC
      - Adjusted shapes of sad, heh-doachashmee, some jeem forms, initial ains,
      and alternate-height kafs and gafs
      - Improved shape of shadda
      - Fixed right side-bearing problems with kafs, gafs, seens, and bariyeh
      - Made bariyeh right-joining only
      - Made many small glyph shape improvements
      - Improved collision handling for special cases
      - Added an omitted feature to TypeTuner capability
      - Redesigned salaam ulena ligature
      - Improved punctuation kerning
      - Include auto-hinting for Latin characters
      - Fixed bug in noon-ring implementation
      - Fixed positioning problems in end of ayah
      
      ### 2017-Jul-17 (SIL NRSI team) Awami Nastaliq Version 1.000
      - Adjusted spacing issues between some characters
      - Adjusted anchors on many glyphs
      - Adjusted digit kerning
      - Adjusted design of Kafs/Gafs/Lams/Meems
      - Fixed font compression problems on OSX
      - Changed design of U+061B
      - Improved design of initial and medial U+067C (teh ring)
      - Removed U+FEFB (lam/alef ligature)
      - Tweaked positioning of some character combinations
      
      ### 2017-Apr-11 (SIL NRSI team) Awami Nastaliq Beta3
      - Changed angle of vertical strokes on alef, lam, kaf, gaf, and tah forms
      - Increased the line height by 20%
      - Changed shapes of a number of letter forms: tah, bariyeh, feh (head shape),
      dal, reh, some meems, some heh-goals, isolate kaf/gaf, some initial jeems,
      pesh, dopesh, name marker
      - Added Arabic style punctuation; cleaned up behavior of Arabic vs. Latin style
      punctuation
      - Added visible versions of invisible characters such as directional markers,
      directional embedding, no-break spaces, etc.
      - Added features: Full stop alternate (dash vs. dot) and Punctuation
      (default, Arabic, or Latin)
      - Added 06CE - yeh with small V; 06D5 - Ae
      - Adjust size of spaces to match rescaling that happened in beta-2 version
      - Fixed bugs in hamza feature
      - Cleaned up positions of diacritics
      
      ### 2016-Dec-7 (SIL NRSI team) Awami Nastaliq Beta2
      - Increased font size by 15%
      - Redesigned seen forms
      - Redesigned nuqtas, made a them little smaller and closer together
      - Implemented feature to allow shorter kafs/gafs and some final forms
      (noon, seen, chotiyeh, bariyeh, qaf, meem, lam) when the sequences
      get very high
      - Added feature to allow alternate position of V over lam
      - Added Arabic style quote marks at a higher position than Latin
      - Scaled subtending marks more appropriately
      - Hand-tweaked some combinations to make more readable
      - Added U+06B0 GAF WITH RING
      - Added "salaam ulena" ligature
      - Redesigned initial beh before meem
      - Made nuqta positions on seens and sads more consistent
      - Reworked ain connections
      - Fixed shape of Arabic 4 and 5
      - Adjusted various letter shapes
      
      ### 2016-Aug-1 (SIL NRSI team) Awami Nastaliq Beta1
      - Beta1 release based on Alpha2 feedback
      - Additional characters and features added
      
      ### 2016-May-16 (SIL NRSI team) Awami Nastaliq Alpha2
      - Alpha2 release based on Alpha1 feedback
      - Additional characters and features added
      
      ### 2015-Dec-04 (SIL NRSI team) Awami Nastaliq Alpha1
      - Preliminary design font for initial feedback
      
      ### 2014-Sep-10 (SIL NRSI team) Awami Nastaliq Preliminary work
      - Preliminary design of isolate characters
    </text>
  </description>
  <license url="https://openfontlicense.org" id="org.openfontlicense.1.1">
    <text lang="en">
      Copyright (c) 2014-2024, SIL International (https://www.sil.org/),
      with Reserved Font Names "Awami" and "SIL".
      
      This Font Software is licensed under the SIL Open Font License, Version 1.1.
      
      This license is copied below, and is also available with an FAQ at:
      https://openfontlicense.org/
      
      ----------------------------------------------------
      SIL OPEN FONT LICENSE Version 1.1 - 26 February 2007
      ----------------------------------------------------
      
      PREAMBLE
      The goals of the Open Font License (OFL) are to stimulate worldwide
      development of collaborative font projects, to support the font creation
      efforts of academic and linguistic communities, and to provide a free and
      open framework in which fonts may be shared and improved in partnership
      with others.
      
      The OFL allows the licensed fonts to be used, studied, modified and
      redistributed freely as long as they are not sold by themselves. The
      fonts, including any derivative works, can be bundled, embedded,
      redistributed and/or sold with any software provided that any reserved
      names are not used by derivative works. The fonts and derivatives,
      however, cannot be released under any other type of license. The
      requirement for fonts to remain under this license does not apply
      to any document created using the fonts or their derivatives.
      
      DEFINITIONS
      "Font Software" refers to the set of files released by the Copyright
      Holder(s) under this license and clearly marked as such. This may
      include source files, build scripts and documentation.
      
      "Reserved Font Name" refers to any names specified as such after the
      copyright statement(s).
      
      "Original Version" refers to the collection of Font Software components as
      distributed by the Copyright Holder(s).
      
      "Modified Version" refers to any derivative made by adding to, deleting,
      or substituting -- in part or in whole -- any of the components of the
      Original Version, by changing formats or by porting the Font Software to a
      new environment.
      
      "Author" refers to any designer, engineer, programmer, technical
      writer or other person who contributed to the Font Software.
      
      PERMISSION &amp; CONDITIONS
      Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining
      a copy of the Font Software, to use, study, copy, merge, embed, modify,
      redistribute, and sell modified and unmodified copies of the Font
      Software, subject to the following conditions:
      
      1) Neither the Font Software nor any of its individual components,
      in Original or Modified Versions, may be sold by itself.
      
      2) Original or Modified Versions of the Font Software may be bundled,
      redistributed and/or sold with any software, provided that each copy
      contains the above copyright notice and this license. These can be
      included either as stand-alone text files, human-readable headers or
      in the appropriate machine-readable metadata fields within text or
      binary files as long as those fields can be easily viewed by the user.
      
      3) No Modified Version of the Font Software may use the Reserved Font
      Name(s) unless explicit written permission is granted by the corresponding
      Copyright Holder. This restriction only applies to the primary font name as
      presented to the users.
      
      4) The name(s) of the Copyright Holder(s) or the Author(s) of the Font
      Software shall not be used to promote, endorse or advertise any
      Modified Version, except to acknowledge the contribution(s) of the
      Copyright Holder(s) and the Author(s) or with their explicit written
      permission.
      
      5) The Font Software, modified or unmodified, in part or in whole,
      must be distributed entirely under this license, and must not be
      distributed under any other license. The requirement for fonts to
      remain under this license does not apply to any document created
      using the Font Software.
      
      TERMINATION
      This license becomes null and void if any of the above conditions are
      not met.
      
      DISCLAIMER
      THE FONT SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND,
      EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTIES OF
      MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT
      OF COPYRIGHT, PATENT, TRADEMARK, OR OTHER RIGHT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
      COPYRIGHT HOLDER BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY,
      INCLUDING ANY GENERAL, SPECIAL, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
      DAMAGES, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
      FROM, OUT OF THE USE OR INABILITY TO USE THE FONT SOFTWARE OR FROM
      OTHER DEALINGS IN THE FONT SOFTWARE.
    </text>
  </license>
  <copyright>
    <text lang="en">
      Copyright (c) 2014-2024, SIL International (https://www.sil.org) with Reserved Font Names "Awami" and "SIL".
    </text>
  </copyright>
  <trademark>
    <text lang="en">Awami Nastaliq is a trademark of SIL International.</text>
  </trademark>
</metadata>